Today's דף Daf is דף ל"ו. Daf Lamed Vav. We start on
ל"ה עמוד ב' Lamed He Amud Bais and let's take a look.
Abaye
and Rav Yosef, two lines from the top of ל"ה עמוד ב',
Lamed He Amud Bais, so we're about a עמוד Amud behind, let's
see if we can catch up. אביי הווה יתיב קמיה דרב יוסף.
Abaye hava yativ kamei deRav Yosef. Abaye was sitting in front of
Rav Yosef. איפסיקא ליה רצועה דתפילין. Ipsika lei retzuah de-tefillin. His רצועה
retzuah broke. Now remember so far we've said that the black of
the תפילין tefillin is הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha LeMoshe MiSinai. Now we're
going to be talking about other aspects of the black of the
רצועה. retzuah. So anyway, his רצועה retzuah broke. אמר ליה, Amar lei,
so he said to Rav Yosef, מהו למקטריה, mahu lemaktrei, can I
knot it? Can I, you know, fix my strap by knotting the
broken halves together? אמר ליה, Amar lei, וקשרתם כתיב. Ukshartem ketiv. It
says you shall bind it, שתהא קשירה תמה, she-tehei keshira tama, it
should be a perfect, unbroken binding, which presumably means that the strap
used for binding cannot be broken. It has to be a whole
strap, or as maybe it can't be two knots, there only has
to be the one knot, but no, you cannot bind your strap.
So אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרב יוסף לרב אשי, Amar lei
Rav Acha brei deRav Yosef leRav Ashi, so he said to Rav
Ashi, מהו למתפריה דאיילי ליה לתפירי ואיהב. mahu lemitfreih de-aylei lei letfiri
ve-yehav. How about not knotting the break, but how about sewing and
putting the sewing, the stitches on the inside?
So somebody who from the outside won't see the stitching. That makes
it look a lot better, that's a real fix. So אמר, Amar,
so he said, פוק חזי מאי עמא דבר. Puk chazi mai ama
devar. Go see what the people are doing. Which
רש"י Rashi says means, and since people don't do it, it's אסור.
assur. And what תוספות Tosafot says means, and since people do it,
it's מותר. mutar.
תוספות Tosafot assumes that פוק חזי מאי עמא דבר Puk chazi mai
ama devar is usually used in a קולא kula context, so that's
why he chooses to read the גמרא Gemara that way. Makes total
sense, right? How often does this happen for us anyway? But you
have to remember we use עור בהמה גסה. or behema gassa. We
use thick leather as opposed to thin leather which might tear so
easily. We also use thick straps as opposed to very thin straps.
But right, how often do you see it anyway? Also problem about
following common practice if it's something that you are, you know, you
don't observe, so what is there to follow? Like if רש"י Rashi
would say, well nobody ever does it, maybe the reason nobody ever
does it is because it doesn't happen. Right, you can only bring
evidence if the situation happens how they deal with it.
Exactly, exactly.
Alright, so anyway that's that. That's about the strap breaking. But now
we're also going to talk about the length of the strap, the
proper length. Let's take a look. אמר רב פפא. Amar Rav Papa.
Was he talking about the ראש rosh or the יד?
yad? Not clear, presumably either, but it'll be a little bit clearer
maybe in a moment. Okay. אמר רב פפא גרדומי רצועות כשרות. Amar
Rav Papa gardumei retzuot kesherot. The remnant of the straps is sufficient.
The phrase גרדומים gardumim basically means that we assume that there's a
requisite length to begin with, but even though you had that requisite
length to begin with, if you're left with a little remnant of
it at the end, you're okay. We have that idea by ציצית.
tzitzit. By ציצית tzitzit there's a certain length that the string of
the ציצית tzitzit has to be to start with, but if after
you made your ציצית tzitzit it tore and there's a little bit
left, it's still okay. So he says when it comes by תפילין,
tefillin, that's כשר. kasher.
Meaning compared to your shoes?
No, no, no, we're talking about is your תפילין tefillin still כשר?
kasher? My תפילין, tefillin, let's say we say the length of the
strap is that it's go down to your waist for the של
ראש, shel rosh, let's say. We'll talk about it in a minute.
So you did that, but then what happened was it ripped, we're
back to it ripping. So he's saying if it's okay if you
have a little bit left here of the strap since it started
at the right length. We're talking that the תפילין tefillin are still
כשר. kasher. Okay.
Is it not that let's say you're making the תפילין tefillin like
you know, and you designate this thick piece of תפילין tefillin and
you have a little left over?
No, that's not that discussion at all. Either of us, it's not
that discussion. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says ולאו מילתא היא, velav
milta hi, that's not correct. מדיאמרי בני רבי חייא, Mid-amri bnei Rabbi
Chiyya, since the sons of Rabbi Chiyya say, גרדומי תכלת וגרדומי אזוב
כשרים, gardumei techelet ve-gardumei ezov kesherim, that if your תכלת techelet here
is a stand-in for all of ציצית, tzitzit, but obviously refers to
the blue of ציצית. tzitzit. So if that string broke and there's
a tiny bit left, it's okay. And similarly if the אזוב, ezov,
you know the hyssop that you do the dipping in for פרה
אדומה Parah Adumah or for the מצורע, Metzora, if that started as
a requisite length and then it broke and you only have a
little left, that's okay. So that's what they taught, that there the
גרדומים, gardumim, the remnant is okay. התם הוא, Hatam hu,
boy these guys are losing the video and their audio. Okay, anyway
I don't know what to say. התם הוא דתשמישי מצוה נינהו. Hatam
hu detashmishei mitzvah ninhu. That's true over there where those things, and
this is extremely important introducing two categories of things used for מצוות.
mitzvot. There it's true that we could be more lenient because those
are things that serve the מצוה. mitzvah. אבל הכא דתשמישי קדושה נינהו
לא. aval hacha detashmishei kedusha ninhu lo. But here where these are
things are called תשמישי קדושה, tashmishei kedusha, we would not be as
lenient. What is the difference? You know what the גמרא Gemara calls
תשמישי מצוה tashmishei mitzvah we would more call like מצוה mitzvah objects.
So things like a ציצית, tzitzit, a לולב, lulav, a שופר, shofar,
those are תשמישי מצוה, tashmishei mitzvah, מצוה mitzvah objects and they have
certain requirements but they don't really have... intrinsic קדושה. Kedusha. Hold on
a second and just try to see. Okay, some music we're fading
it
up although we're into it now. Is there a commercial break?
No, no, yes now okay. I don't know what's going on. Now
we seem to be okay.
Anyway, so those things are mitzvah objects. Mitzvah objects don't have intrinsic
קדושה. Kedusha. They have... it's because they're used to do a מצוה
Mitzvah that they're significant. And therefore the primary laws that govern their
use,
in terms of the respect you show them, is during the period
of the מצוה. Mitzvah. After the period of the מצוה, Mitzvah, like
what do you do with your לולב Lulav afterwards? You're not supposed
to throw it out in your trash, but basically you can wrap
it in a plastic bag and just don't dispose of it in
a disrespectful way. Now we try to use them for doing another
מצוה, Mitzvah, so the whole idea of using your leftover לולב Lulav
for the fire for making מצות, Matzos,
or I don't know, same thing from the one on top of
the other.
We have one on top of the other. I have some at
home. Anybody that needs some לולבים Lulavs for making your מצות, Matzos,
please let me know. I've got a few. Anyway, for
burning their חמץ. Chometz. Anyway, that's what you try to do with
it. But מעיקר הדין, Mikar Hadin, once the מצוה Mitzvah is done,
there's basically no real laws that govern it. And even during the
time, the amount of respect that
or laws that define its use are not so weighty. That's as
opposed to תשמישי מצוה... Tashmishei Mitzvah... תשמישי קדושה. Tashmishei Kedusha.
תשמישי קדושה Tashmishei Kedusha are things that are associated basically with כיסא
הקודש Kisei Hakodesh or maybe a little more specifically שם השם. Shem
Hashem. And therefore those things because of the association with שם השם
Shem Hashem and כיסא הקודש, Kisei Hakodesh, those things have a much
higher level of קדושה. Kedusha. And that's not just when the מצוה
Mitzvah is being used, that's a status that's just intrinsically associated with
it. It's why if it stops being usable you put it into
שמות Sheimes and all these types of things. You never put your
לולב Lulav into שמות. Sheimes. That's תשמישי קדושה. Tashmishei Kedusha. So תפילין
Tefillin are תשמישי קדושה. Tashmishei Kedusha. Why? Not because you do a
מצוה Mitzvah with it. From that angle they're תשמישי...
guys I don't know what's going on with your audio. We've been
having some internet problems today.
Anyway, so from that
perspective, I'm going to set
it here.
We'll see if that makes this any better.
But
let's say it was a ספר תורה Sefer Torah, that had too
many mistakes from the very beginning, would that still be a תשמישי
קדושה? Tashmishei Kedusha? Yeah, I think so.
So it's not even if it was used, it doesn't have to
be like משומש. Meshumash. No, no.
He's a better expert than me.
All
right, I hope it's better everybody. I'm going to stop this and
then start it again.
Tell me if it's any better.
Of all the logistics you ever get a שיעור Shiur taught in
the core thing...
You need a CTO.
I need a שמש Shamash is what I need. All right, anyway,
so that's תשמישי מצוה... Tashmishei Mitzvah... תשמישי קדושה. Tashmishei Kedusha.
What was your question? Yeah, it doesn't matter that it was a
כשר Kosher ספר תורה, Sefer Torah? it matters that it was a
verse with שם השם Shem Hashem and so on. That תפילין Tefillin
are תשמישי מצוה, Tashmishei Mitzvah, you use them to do a מצוה
Mitzvah with, but they also are תשמישי קדושה Tashmishei Kedusha because they're
connected to the קלפים Klafim on the inside. And interesting קלפים Klafim
on the inside, I'll get to in a minute, is what is
the status of the בית Bayis itself with the שין Shin on
it of the של ראש? Shel Rosh?
Oh you say you want to do a משנה Mishna yesterday.
Yeah, well so I get to
so תוספות Tosafos says that that של ראש, Shel Rosh, that might
be because it's connected to a שין Shin which is part of
שם השם, Shem Hashem, that might not just be תשמישי קדושה, Tashmishei
Kedusha, that might be actual you know קדושה Kedusha itself, like כיסא
הקודש Kisei Hakodesh or something, something that has שם השם Shem Hashem
on it. It's not just serving the קלפים Klafim on the inside.
We wouldn't call the קלפים Klafim תשמישי קדושה, Tashmishei Kedusha, we'd call
them כיסא הקודש. Kisei Hakodesh. Anyway, we'll get to that in a
minute.
So, going back to this, the גמרא Gemara says look, now here's
an interesting thing. Normally we assume the difference between תשמישי מצוה Tashmishei
Mitzvah and תשמישי קדושה Tashmishei Kedusha are what type of a respect
you have to show the object and שמות Sheimes and those types
of questions. But here the גמרא Gemara says since ציצית Tzitzis are
תשמישי קדושה... Tashmishei Kedusha... if they break you can be יוצא Yotzei
with a little bit. But since תפילין Tefillin are תשמישי... I'm sorry,
ציצית Tzitzit are תשמישי מצוה. Tashmishei Mitzvah. Since תפילין Tefillin are תשמישי
קדושה, Tashmishei Kedusha, we're going to assume weightier requirements and we're going
to assume you need the full length of the רצועה. Retzuah. It's
not good if it broke and a little left off, which personally
I don't understand at all. Because first of all we're looking at
תפילין Tefillin from its role as תשמישי מצוה. Tashmishei Mitzvah. We're not
asking do I have to put it in שמות. Sheimes. We're asking
can I be יוצא Yotzei the מצוה Mitzvah of תפילין. Tefillin. So
it's what we're looking at it from its dimension of תשמישי מצוה.
Tashmishei Mitzvah. Number one. And number two even if it is תשמישי
קדושה, Tashmishei Kedusha, it's not exactly clear to me why that should
be the higher criteria. So I'm not exactly sure the logic that
the גמרא Gemara is making here. But it is saying that because
it is תשמישי מצוה, Tashmishei Mitzvah, therefore a remnant is not... the
only thing I can maybe imagine, and maybe this is what sort
of Michael was thinking about before,
is that maybe because if there is a law
of like שמות... Sheimes... off is more of a problem, right, it's
not like if you're, you know, if the bottom part of your
lulav, let's say you rip off a lulav leaf, you know, what
do you do with it? You put it in the garbage. It's
no longer serving its mitzvah purpose. So the fact that something broke
off is not so much a problem, then it stops being associated.
Here, the sense of it belongs there and it's taken away from
it by the tefillin strap is higher because of the concept of
תשמישי קדושה. Tashmishey Kedusha. So maybe that makes the issue of גרדומין
Gardumin more problematic as well. Not clear to me, but that's how
the גמרא Gemara concludes, and therefore breaking the tefillin strap is not
going to be good; you need the full length. Yes.
So I guess, so your the case is, I'm just trying to
understand this, is let's say it needs to be a foot long
and you only have an inch long, right? Let's say it was
a foot long, you made it two feet long, now what... No,
it's only when it goes
less than the initial שיעור. Shiur. We don't know yet what the
initial שיעור Shiur is. גרדומין Gardumin is it started the right שיעור
Shiur and now it's less than the initial.
The minimal to maintain kashrut.
But we don't know yet what that minimal שיעור Shiur is. So
let's take... but what was more but הלכה Halacha by ציצית Tzitzit
because when your ציצית Tzitzit tear, they can still be כשר Kosher
even if they weren't כשר Kosher that way if you had made
them that way initially.
But if it was more and now it's the right שיעור Shiur
you're no problem. Yes, exactly. It's not a matter of like if
it doesn't look as nice anymore. Correct. Correct. There seemed that there
was an issue, you
know, but not here, not here. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, it's only there by like ציצית tzitzit. which is תשמישי מצווה,
Tashmishey Mitzvah, not here by tefillin which is תשמישי קדושה. Tashmishey Kedusha.
So the גמרא Gemara says בכלל, Bichlal, so okay from this whole
discussion I accept that גרדומין Gardumin is not good, but from this
discussion I can infer דאית להו שיעורא De'isu lehu shiura that there
is a minimum size of the length of the רצועה. Retzuah. כמה
שיורייהו? Kamma shiuraihu? What is its minimal שיעור? Shiur? אמר רבי בר
חמא אמר ריש לקיש עד אצבע צרדא, Amar Rabbi Bar Chama Amar
Resh Lakish ad etzba tzerada, until your snapping finger, which רש"י Rashi
says means your snapping finger, which רש"י Rashi says means your actually
רש"י Rashi says it means your forefinger, תוספות Tosafot says you don't
snap with your forefinger, תוספות Tosafot says it means your middle finger.
Okay. עד אצבע צרדא, Ad etzba tzerada, I will say in a
minute what this means. רב כהנא מחוי כפוף, Rav Kahana machvei kaphuf,
רב כהנא Rav Kahana demonstrated, showed like if it were bent. רב
אשי מחוי פשוט, Rav Ashi machvei pashut, רב אשי Rav Ashi demonstrated
as if it were straightened out. What does this mean? So two
explanations. One רש"י Rashi says means it's just a finger length, so
it's basically the length between your thumb and your forefinger according to
רש"י, Rashi, according to תוספות Tosafot it would be your thumb and
your middle finger, but a unit of length, that's how long it
has to be presumably after the knot of the של ראש, Shel
Rosh, how far it has to go down presumably, it's not clear,
or maybe that point of the יסוד יד Yesod Yad after the
ring, and the... that's כפוף Kaphuf which is like very widely spread
and פשוט Pashut which רש"י Rashi says like not widely spread would
be like this, basically about half a length. That's one explanation both
רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot adopt although they debate which is the
finger we're talking about. The other explanation though is, which is what
Michael was thinking, is no, we're talking about the של יד Shel
Yad and we mean it has to get all the way to
your middle finger from here, and that's actually how we פוסקין. Pasken.
And then the only difference between כפוף Kaphuf and פשוט Pashut is
are we talking that your finger's bent down, so it'd be enough
to get to like the palm of your hand, that's כפוף, Kaphuf,
or are we talking about straightened and it would have to get
out there, and that's basically what we rule, it has to be
long enough, we make like seven wraps, that's not really required הלכה
להלכה, halacha le'halacha, you can do one wrap here and then go
to your finger. But that's how long it has to be to
get after the one sort of tightening and not to get to
your finger by the של יד. Shel Yad. How long does the
של ראש Shel Rosh have to be if our גמרא Gemara is
talking about the של יד? Shel Yad? The גמרא Gemara doesn't say.
The שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch actually does not really say very clearly
how long the של ראש Shel Rosh have to be. If you
look at the bottom of תוספות Tosafot פוק חזי, Puk chazi, תוספות
Tosafot says like
this, ושימושא רבא, U'vi'shimusha rabba,
again I have to find out more about this work, so there's
this work called שימושא רבא Shimusha Rabba which they're always quoting about
in הלכות תפילין, Hilchos Tefillin, it must I think it was some
גאוני Geonic work that had a lot there about הלכות תפילין. Hilchos
Tefillin. So near the end of this תוספות, Tosafot, about six lines
before it's over, he says like
this: ושימושא
רבא דתפילין יש דליבעי שיעור רצועות עד דלימטי לחדא כנגד מילה. U'vishimusha
rabba d'tefillin yesh d'livshir retzuai ad d'limti l'chada k'neged mila. So
one of the רצועות Retzuos coming down from your של ראש, Shel
Rosh, one of them has to reach your מילה, Mila, which basically
is below the waist, מימינה, mi'ymina,
that's on the right hand side, וחדא כנגד הלב משמאלה, v'chada k'neged
ha'lev mi'smola,
and one of them has to get to your heart on the
left. תוספות Tosafot earlier quoted an opinion that on your right it
doesn't have to go all the way below the waist, it has
to get more or less to your belly button. Okay.
And then he has a discussion about how wide it is. עוד
יש אומר דמצוה שיעור רוחב הרצועות, Od yesh omer de'mitzvah shiur rochav
ha'retzuos, how wide, יותר מחיטה, yoser mi'chita, better to be wider than
a wheat, grain of wheat, ופחות משעורה, u'pachus mi'se'ora, but smaller than
a barley grain. If it's more כשר, Kasher, but if it's bigger
it really isn't a problem. Ours are
much wider than that. Yes. Anyway, it says not problem if it's
bigger. Yes, I don't know where they're getting from, a lot of
this they're getting it from tradition, but here it's amazing, the גמרא
Gemara most you know might be talking about a של יד Shel
Yad and then there's all these weird ideas about a של ראש
Shel Rosh which are about this far for the right, this far
for the left. It does become an issue when the תפילין tefillin
actually does break, or when, like we talked about yesterday, the black
wears off, because if you say that if it's the part beyond
the שיעור, shiur, it's not a problem. If it's the part within
the שיעור, shiur, it is a problem. Okay, and it is quite
interesting that the גמרא Gemara is not clear if it's של יד,
shel yad, של ראש, shel rosh, what it's talking about, and תוספות
Tosafot is trying to fill the gap. In the first case...
Yeah, for all of this you could leave it there, or you
could cut it off before the where it's not black.
That's a good point. I think it's even not a problem. I
hear your point that maybe you can just, you know,
maybe if it's cut off, it's not part of it, but if
it's not cut off, it's still considered part of it. I think
we say that even if you don't cut it off, if it's
beyond the שיעור, shiur, it's not an issue. But I'd have to
double check that.
Right, and you're saying it's this long according to one way of
explaining it, that after you made the knot? Yeah, you make one
knot, a little bit more on your arm, you know, that length
more on your arm after you tied it. That after you do
this, it has to reach all the way to your middle finger,
yeah, according to the first explanation.
According to the second
explanation, it's just this length after you do the knot, presumably after
you do the knot, depending on how you tie it, right? Perfect.
Now I did want to say something. I'm going to cheat a
little and I know we're behind, but I couldn't resist, because we
had discussed רש"י Rashi and רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam and now you
see in תוספות Tosafot also this whole question about being influenced by
these other books, שימושא רבא Shimusha Rabba and so on. The רש"י
רבנו תם Rashi Rabbeinu Tam תפילין tefillin was not just רש"י רבנו
תם. Rashi Rabbeinu Tam. רמב"ם'ס Rambam's quote says like רש"י, Rashi, the
ראב"ד Ra'avad critiques the רמב"ם, Rambam, there are others he basically shows
the position of רבנו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, you know, it's not just
רמב"ם Rambam and ראב"ד, Ra'avad, it's not just רש"י Rashi and רבנו
תם, Rabbeinu Tam, you know, it's a larger issue. So there's a
famous תשובה teshuva that they asked the רמב"ם Rambam
about which order you put your תפילין tefillin in, and they said,
we see what you wrote in משנה תורה, Mishneh Torah, but we
had this other tradition about הויות באמצע, havayot b'emtza, you know, which
is basically רבנו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, what should we do? And I
just want to read you one line of his answer where he
says, I made copies of it but I'll just read it now
quickly, he says like this, he says, it's a really fascinating answer,
he says like this: כך ידעתי מקודם ככם, kach yadati mikodem kachem,
I used to think like you, like רבנו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, like
הויות באמצע. havayot b'emtza. ותפילין שהיו לי בארץ מערב, utfillin shehayu li
b'eretz maarav,
when I was still living in the West, in Spain, כך היו,
kach hayu,
those were my תפילין, tefillin, that they were like רבנו תם, Rabbeinu
Tam, I mean he's not saying רבנו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, but they
were הויות באמצע. havayot b'emtza. וכתב כזה אותו אחר שחיבר חיבור התפילין
ושמו רב משה מקורדובה. v'kosev kaze oso achar shechibar chibur hatefillin ushmo
Rav Moshe miCordoba.
So this was because it was influenced by a book written about
laws of תפילין tefillin by רב משה Rav Moshe of Cordoba. Interesting,
in some texts of the תשובה, teshuva, it says רב משה בר
מימון מקורדובה,
Rav Moshe bar
Maimon miCordoba, obviously not the doctor, but there was another רב משה
Rav Moshe of Cordoba that wrote laws of תפילין tefillin and people
followed it and basically was like רבנו תם'ס Rabbeinu Tam's position and
had הויות באמצע. havayot b'emtza. רמב"ם Rambam says that was my תפילין.
tefillin. And he says: ואותו חיבור הוא שהטעני והטע כל אנשי המערב
מלפני. v'oso chibur hu shehatani v'hata kol anshei hamaarav milfanai.
That is what made me err and what led astray all of
the people of the West that they followed. So it shows you,
you know, the power of codes, the power of, you know, of
something that's written and it becomes sort of the guide and the
manual and how much that influenced the practice. And then he said
even the רי"ף Rif actually in one תשובה teshuva indicates this idea
of הויות באמצע. havayot b'emtza. And then he goes on and says,
and what, how did I, what made me ultimately go back to
the other position, which, you know, we would call רש"י תפילין. Rashi
tefillin. So he says like this, and for some reason this did
not collate, it's one of those technical days. He says like this,
anyway, he says a lot of גאונים, Geonim, he says like this,
he says: חילוקו של דבר זה, chiluko shel davar zeh, a lot
of גאונים, Geonim,
the breakdown of this matter, and אנשי מזרח, anshei mizrach, the people
of the East, ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, ואל אנשי ארץ צבי, v'al
anshei Eretz Tzvi, the people of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, הקדמונים חולקים
עליו. hakadmonim cholkim alav. Okay, and now listen to this, talking about,
you know, this stuff that sounds to us very modern. Okay, he
says: ואמרו לי חכמים נאמנים שפתחו תפילין של
הגאון רבינו האי ז"ל. v'amru li chachamim ne'emanim shepatechu tefillin shel haGaon
Rabbeinu Hai zal. They opened up his תפילין tefillin after he died
presumably, because רבנו האי Rabbeinu Hai was quoted as basically saying הויות
באמצע havayot b'emtza like רבנו תם. Rabbeinu Tam. They opened up his
תפילין tefillin ומצאו אותן כתובים על הסדר שאמרתי בחיבור. umatzau osan ketuvim
al haseder she'amarti b'chibur. And they found that they were like what
I said, it was the normal way they're written. And then he
says, and then he has one other line and he says like
this: והברייתא הברורה בדבר זה, v'habraita habrurah b'davar zeh, the proof that
I'm right, that it's the right way they're written in the... in
the תורה, Torah, נאמר בפרק הקומץ, ne'emar b'perek haKomatz, קורא על סדר
התורה. korei al seder haTorah. So remember we had about קורא קורא
על סדר, korei korei al seder, but it ended very cryptically. Oh,
and you read it in order. What order? In order in which
way? So he has, here was the גרסא girsa that I had
in the גמרא. Gemara. קורא קורא על סדר התורה, korei korei al
seder haTorah, קדש לי והיה כי יביאך שמע והיה אם שמוע. Kadesh
Li, V'haya Ki Yeviacha, Shema, V'haya Im Shamoa. So when he found
a נוסח nusach of the גמרא Gemara that explicitly gave the order
in the sequential order... and then he says: ונוסח זה לא היה
בספרים שלנו בארץ מערב. v'nusach zeh lo haya basfarim shelanu b'eretz maarav.
This was not in our manuscripts in the West, in Spain. But
he says: אבל הנה מצאתי כל
הנוסחאות הישנות וכך כתוב בהן. aval hinei matzati kol hanuschaot hayeshanot v'kach
katuv bahen. Just
like
we have it, right?
No, we don't have קדש והיה אם שמוע. Kadesh V'haya Im Shamoa.
קדש לי והיה כי יביאך,
Kadesh Li,
V'haya Ki Yeviacha,
no, דימין, de-yamin, שמע והיה אם שמוע דשמאל. Shema V'haya Im Shamoa
de-smol. He had what is very cryptic. He had the מסקנא maskana
at the end with קורא קורא על הסדר, korei korei al haseder,
קדש והיה כי יביאך שמע והיה אם שמוע. Kadesh V'haya Ki Yeviacha
Shema V'haya Im Shamoa. would be the order.
מימין
*Miyamin* or שמאל
*Smol*?
Right. Straight. So anyway, he says, I found a manuscript and that's
what they do in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael, *Eretz Yisrael* and so
anyway there was an article that basically said that he thinks it
was because of the רמב״ם *Rambam*'s this תשובה *teshuva*, again, it's all
speculation, that totally turned the tide. Maybe if it wasn't for this,
we'd all be wearing רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam *Rabbeinu Tam* תפילין Tefillin,
*tefillin*. But if you read this תשובה *teshuva*, you see it was
not just like a weird opinion of רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam *Rabbeinu
Tam*, it was widespread in Spain, maybe in Provence, you know, wherever
he came from, they were all influenced by this one book that
this רב משה Moshe קורדובירו *Rav Moshe Cordova* wrote, and a lot
of the גאונים *Geonim*, and he really turned the tide by emphasizing
what his manuscripts were, רב האי *Rav Hai*'s תפילין Tefillin, *tefillin*. It's
a fact if you think about the sort of more academic things.
We're going to actually look at the reality. Let's open up רב
האי *Rav Hai*'s תפילין Tefillin *tefillin*. Let's check the manuscripts. And then
he said, and I also go by ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* because
they have stronger traditions about תפילין Tefillin *tefillin*. They're more מקפיד *makpid*
about תפילין Tefillin *tefillin*. And does that have a lot to do
with sort of turning the tide and why now we sort of...
I don't know, that this... there's an article that speculates that it's
this תשובה *teshuva* that turned the tide. But it's fascinating to realize
how widespread the practices were and also since such little is from
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, if I'm going to write to you, here's
a handbook for תפילין Tefillin, *tefillin* and you're a סופר *sofer*, right,
what are you going to do? You're just going to open up
two dozen pairs of תפילין Tefillin. *tefillin* and see how they're written?
No, you'll use my handbook. So, you know, the influence that these
handbooks could have played. And תוספות Tosfot *Tosefot* is constantly quoting this
ספר שימושא רבא Sefer Shimusha Rabba *Sefer Shimusha Rabba*.
This is only 24 permutations and how... how do we only really
have two major themes in it? Yeah, we've... we've obviously got some...
רב האי גאון *Hai Gaon* was what, like 10th century?
רב האי גאון *Hai Gaon* was, I think, 10th. He was one
of the latest גאונים *Geonim*. Yeah. So.
But if there are 24 permutations, how has it been distilled to
two? I mean, because he said that, you know, didn't...
they are the two reasonable reads of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, the
two ones that actually got...
the two ones in the... if he said they found a whole
bunch of them in קומראן *Kumran*.
Yeah, so I don't know, that was קומראן *Kumran*. But once the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* was there, that limited the range of reasonable possibilities.
Okay, so let's continue.
רבא *Raba* says like this.
Exactly. Okay, so let's continue. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this.
Okay, so now we have the question about... about how long the
רצועות *retzuot* have to be. רבא קטרא להו פשיט ושדי לה *Raba
katra lehu pashit vesharila*. רבא *Raba* was קושר *kosher* his תפילין Tefillin
*tefillin* and tossed it. What does tossed it mean? רש״י *Rashi* says
it means like he flung the רצועות *retzuot* behind his back.
Okay. של ראש Shel Rosh. *Shel rosh* presumably, right? של ראש Shel
Rosh.
*Shel rosh*, yeah. רב אחא בר יעקב קטרא להו מפיק להו *Rav
Acha bar Yaakov katra lehu mappik lehu*. No, he after he was
קושר *kosher* it, he hung it, meaning hung it in front is
where he put the רצועות *retzuot*.
And then it says, רב אחא בר יעקב הוי עביד *Rav Acha
bar Yaakov hava avid*, ומר בריה דרבינא עביד כדידן *umar brei deRavina
avid kedidan*, and מר בריה דרבינא *Mar brei deRavina* did like we
do, where רש״י *Rashi* says means hung from in front. But again,
this is fascinating. You would think the idea that they have to
come down in front is a pretty strong הלכה halacha *halacha*. Here
it just makes it sound like it was just different practices. Some
guys did it that way, some guys did it the other way.
In a way, it's almost more natural that it flows behind, you
know. You just think about it as like a headdress and then
it like flows behind. All right, anyway, so that's what you do
with the straps of the תפילין tefillin? *tefillin*. אמר רב יהודה בריה
דרב שמואל בר שילת משמיה דרב *Amar Rav Yehuda brei deRav Shmuel
bar Shilat mishmeih deRav*, קשר של תפילין kesher shel tefillin. הלכה halachically
למשה מסיני *kesher shel tefillin halacha leMoshe miSinai*. The קשר kesher *kesher*
that you make is הלכה halacha למשה מסיני *halacha leMoshe miSinai*. Now
what does this mean? How you make it? רש״י *Rashi* says the
fact that the של ראש Shel Rosh *shel rosh* looks like a
דלת *dalet* and the, you know, של יד Shel Yad *shel yad*
looks like a יוד *yud* and that forms the name of God's
name, שדי *Shakai*,
רש״י *Rashi* says that's הלכה halakha למשה מסיני *halacha leMoshe miSinai*.
תוספות Tosfot *Tosefot* questions whether the actual, you know, using of the
רצועות *retzuot* to form like שם השם Shem Hashem. *shem Hashem*, is
that... is that really counted like a דלת *dalet* and a יוד
*yud* and that really gives
it the status of שם השם Shem Hashem. *shem Hashem*. But the
question is, what is at least הלכה halacha למשה מסיני *halacha leMoshe
miSinai*? Does that mean what... what does he say then קשר kesher
תפילין tefillin *kesher tefillin* means? You know, he's not denying that there's
a way to make it, but he's maybe denying its significance as
a... sort of calling it part of שם השם Shem Hashem, *shem
Hashem*. Okay, but he says it's still הלכה למשה מסיני *halacha leMoshe
miSinai*. Whatever there is, it does tell you, A, that you need
a קשר kesher. *kesher*, B, maybe some of the way it looks.
It's not exactly clear. And by the way, you should be aware
there's a big מחלוקת *machlokes* about what the דלת *dalet* in the
back of the head looks like. There's your standard דלת *dalet*, which
is somehow to make it that shaped like, you know, a perpendicular
or whatever. And then there's something which I used to wear for
many years, which is called a double דלת *dalet*, which is a...
obviously דלת *dalet* is like a square. If it's a double דלת
*dalet*, it's because if you put two דלת *dalet*s together, it looks
like a square. Why I stopped, because it has very little basis
in הלכה *halacha*. It was more like this חסידיק *Chassidic* מנהג minhag
*minhag*. So I actually switched it to the דלת *dalet*. And the
question is, all of these is, are you saying that you're not
יוצא yotzei. *yotze* if you did it the other way? At what
point are we saying that it's פסול pasul *pasul*? If הלכה למשה
מסיני *halacha leMoshe miSinai*, which aspect of it is הלכה למשה מסיני
*halacha leMoshe miSinai*, right? That you have it? The... is it the
shape? Is it, you know, is it the fact that it has
to be black or whatever? That... that is not clear. Okay. אמר
רב נחמן Amar Rav Nachman, ונוייהן לבר *Amar Rav Nachman venoyeihen lebar*.
And we... we put the... the nice part on the outside, which
basically means the black faces out. Okay, as we sort of said
before. רב אשי הוה יתיב קמיה דמר זוטרא *Rav Ashi hava yativ
kamie deMar Zutra*. רב אשי *Rav Ashi* was in front of מר
זוטרא *Mar Zutra*. איתפכא ליה רצועה דתפילין *itpacha lei retzua de-tefillin*. And
his רצועה *retzua* turned. The... the inside part flipped on the out.
It was the של ראש Shel Rosh *shel rosh* or של יד
Shel Yad, *shel yad*, not clear. More likely happened on the של
ראש Shel Rosh *shel rosh*. אמר ליה לא סבר ליה מר ונוייהן
לבר *Amar lei lo savar lei mar venoyeihen lebar*? Don't you agree
that we're supposed to keep the nice part on the outside, the
black part on the outside? אמר ליה לאו אדעתאי *Amar lei lav
ada'atai*. Oh, thank you for pointing that out, I wasn't paying attention.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says... So they'll see that
it's on the ראש rosh that's high up on the head. Now
here, תוספות Tosfot just says it's because of exactly that, that it's
high up on the head, they see it better, it's more visual
than seeing somebody wearing תפילין של ראש. Tefillin Shel Rosh. Not only
that, the גמרא Gemara says, by it says ויהיו לאות על ידיך,
V'yehyu l'ot al yadecha, that the של יד Shel Yad should be
לך, Lecha, ויהיה לך לאות, V'haya lecha l'ot, ולא לכם לאות, V'lo
lachem l'ot, and that's why we cover the של יד, Shel Yad
so if people are seeing you're wearing תפילין, tefillin it's focusing on
the של ראש. Shel Rosh, That's all makes a lot of sense.
רש"י Rashi adds to it that why it's שם השם נקרא עליך,
Shem Hashem nikra alecha, here's what רש"י Rashi says, because of the
ש Shin and the ד Dalet is two thirds of שם השם.
Shem Hashem. And here's where תוספות Tosfot says, no. There might be
a ש Shin on the תפילין, tefillin but the ד Dalet isn't
a real ד, Dalet, the י Yud isn't a real י, Yud,
don't start calling it שם השם. Shem Hashem And part of what
תוספות Tosfot says is that we call the תפילין תשמישי קדושה, Tefillin
tashmishei kedusha, not קדושה עצמו. kedusha atzmo. And if we really thought
that this was forming שם השם, Shem Hashem it wouldn't just be
serving the קלפים klafim and תשמישי קדושה, tashmishei kedusha, it would be
actual קדושה kedusha itself. So תוספות Tosfot downplays the emphasizing of the
forming I mean, which just means he disagrees that that's how you
make the knot, but just it doesn't have a הלכה status of
שם השם.
Shem Hashem. Are they no more holy than a מזוזה mezuzah case?
No, no, no, because the מזוזה mezuzah is תשמיש דתשמיש.
tashmish detashmish. The תפילין tefillin are serving the קלפים, klafim, the case
is serving the תפילין tefillin. which are serving the קלפים. klafim. Are
they no more holy than, let's say, like the, like the what
do you call it? Like the what's it called? The mantle that
you put on the ספר תורה? Sefer Torah? Like that would be
the better comparison. It's directly being משמש meshamesh כתבי קודש. kitvei kodesh.
And the answer might be that in terms of its קדושה, kedusha,
no, but it's also תשמישי מצוה. tashmishei mitzvah. A תפילין tefillin is
two things: תשמישי מצוה, tashmishei mitzvah, it's a מצוה mitzvah object, and
it's serving the קלפים klafim inside. It's תשמישי קדושה. tashmishei kedusha. Okay,
but תוספות Tosfot says that קדושה עצמו, kedusha atzmo, what's not really
שם השם Shem Hashem written on the תפילין, tefillin okay, on the
actual leather of the תפילין.
tefillin You see the ש Shin as the ד, Dalet, but of
course the same shape that makes the י. Yud. What?
The knot? You see the ש Shin as the ד, Dalet, but
with the same shape as the י. Yud.
Well, the י Yud on your you mean the ד Dalet more
or less looks like a י. Yud.
No, the knot is also a י. Yud.
No, the י, Yud, the knot on the של יד Shel Yad
is the י. Yud. You're saying they basically look the same. No,
the knot on the של יד Shel Yad? is very different than
the knot on the של ראש. Shel Rosh
Now, if you wanted to say that neither looks too much like
either letter, that's what תוספות Tosfot says. תוספות Tosfot. says, don't tell
me this is a real letter, okay? But at least the של
יד Shel Yad and של ראש Shel Rosh, are made different. Now,
תוספות Tosfot has a fascinating idea about this. We treat the תפילין
tefillin? exactly like this. What, you're telling me it's no different than
the mantle of a ספר תורה? Torah I want to show you
an amazing, I know we're getting a little behind, but an amazing
line in תוספות. Tosfot תוספות Tosfot again, this אלו תפילין שבראש, eilu
tefillin shebarosh, about four lines before the lines get wide, last two
words of the line, תוספות Tosfot says the following: He says הר"ר
יעקב מאורלינש HaRebbe Yaakov m'Orleans מסתפק mispakek so not New Orleans, Orleans
was doubted, had a question, אם צריך לחלוץ תפילין של יד כשנכנס
לבית הכסא. im tzarich lachlotz tefillin shel yad k'shenichnas l'veit hakisei. You're
going to the bathroom, do you have to take off your של
יד? Shel Yad דשמא כיון דמכוסה בעור לא צריך deshama kivan demichusa
b'or lo tzarich it's covered with leather. Now what's covered with leather?
Not the boxes, the parchment is covered with leather. The parchment is
what's the problem of bringing into the בית הכסא. beit hakisei. הלכה
you're allowed to walk with your מזוזה mezuzah into the בית- bayit
not the מזוזה, your לולב lulav into the בית הכסא. beit hakisei.
Not only that, every single time you go into the בית הכסא
beit hakisei you walk with תשמישי מצוה tashmishei mitzvah into it. Your
ציצית. tzitzit, So you can walk with the תשמישי מצוה tashmishei mitzvah
into the בית הכסא. beit hakisei. You can't walk with the parchment.
One minute. But the question is maybe they're covered with leather, it's
not a problem. So why is the של ראש shel rosh. different?
And then he says דלא אסרו אלא תפילין
של ראש שקשור ש בעור. delo asru ela tefillin shel rosh shekashur
shin ba'or. So maybe that ש shin makes the של ראש shel
rosh, a quasi like כיסא הקודש kisei hakodesh itself. It has part
of שם השם or a letter that represents שם השם. So here
you're so right. So A, that might be a different voice than
the one he was saying before, but even if he denies that
you have real ש ד י, shin dalet yud, he might admit
that at least the ש shin gives it some weight. So here
you actually have a really, you know, hair-splitting, what is this thing
of תפילין? tefillin I'm not sure if this answers your question. There's
a הלכה answer, it's not a philosophical answer, but anyway, it's both
תשמישי מצוה, tashmishei mitzvah, right, which is like ציצית, tzitzis
and it's תשמישי קדושה tashmishei kedusha because it's serving the קלפים klafim
inside. Is it קדושה עצמו? kedusha atzmo? Well, maybe the ש, shin,
maybe the של ראש, shel rosh that we can talk about. To
the point that תוספות Tosafot thinks that if the של יד Shel
Yad which is only תשמישי קדושה tashmishei kedusha and תשמישי מצוה, tashmishei
mitzvah, but the actual כיסא הקודש kisei hakodesh themselves are covered, maybe
you can walk with your של יד Shel Yad, into the bathroom,
and maybe it's only a problem with the של ראש shel rosh,
which actually has that exposed ש. shin.
So he's saying not the box to cover... No, neither.
The actual leather box itself covers the קלפים. klafim.
So the של יד shel yad is covered.
Yeah, but no, no, but that- but he's not saying- he's saying
the קלפים klafim inside the בית are covered, and the קלפים klafim
are the only thing you're really not allowed to bring into the
bathroom. Okay.
He said before that the cover... yes, but that's not what תוספות
Tosafot is talking about, right?
But an anthropologist might say that it's easier to take off the
של ראש, shel rosh it's more difficult to take off the של
יד, shel yad and reasonably go to the bathroom with ארבע כנפות
arba kanfot and don't take off your טלית.
tallit. Interesting. But you could go in with a טלית. tallit. Yeah,
but his point is that maybe they- Know maybe that informs one
another as well, right? For example also you know what else you
don't go into? You don't go into... do you know we say
you're not supposed to go into the bathroom with like a קיטל?
kittel? Like if you're wearing it on יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? Why?
Because they say well because it's a בגד מיוחד לתפילה. beged meyuchad
litfila. Now I don't know, I'm about to wear my קיטל kittel
at the סדר Seder night, so maybe it's not so מיוחד לתפילה,
meyuchad litfila, but anyway... but it also had to do with some
of this issue about well okay and also you can take it
off. Easy to take off. So all right. So anyway there you
have a very interesting discussion about the weight of שם השם on
the actual box itself and the idea of תפילין tefillin as תשמישי
קדושה tashmishe kedusha or תשמישי מצוה. tashmishe mitzva. Okay so let's continue.
A little more אגדתא. aggadata.
תניא, Tanya, we taught.
רבי אליעזר הגדול אומר וסירותי את כפי וראית את אחורי. Rabbi Eliezer
Hagadol omer vehasiroti et kapi vera'ita et achorai. God says to משה
Moshe I will remove my hands and you'll see my back. So
אמר רב חנא בר ביזנא אמר רבי שמעון חסידא מלמד שהראה לו
הקדוש ברוך הוא למשה קשר של תפילין. Amar Rav Hanna bar Bizna
Amar Rabbi Shimon Chasida Melamed sheherah lo Hakadosh Baruch Hu leMoshe kesher
shel tefillin. So what's the back of God? Back of God's head?
Well what do you see? You see the קשר of the תפילין
tefillin because God wears תפילין tefillin. which is a famous גמרא Gemara
in ברכות. Berakhot. I did not have enough time to give some...
to come up with some profound explanation for this but
the idea of all the things that משה Moshe sees is the
קשר של תפילין. kesher shel tefillin You imagine the גמרא Gemara is
not just pointing out well sort of like what you know what
happens to be at the back of God's head, but there's some
significance about that קשר של תפילין kesher shel tefillin that right now
I don't have it.
In
משה's Moshe time? תפילין tefillin at משה's?
Moshe God commanded it in the תורה Torah so presumably yes, and
the גמרא Gemara understands that even God wears תפילין. tefillin.
God stood in the pray before
as
long as the משכן Mishkan was there?
You don't have to wear תפילין tefillin, when you pray, you wear
תפילין tefillin whatever, it's the whole day. תורה Torah doesn't say you
wear it when you pray,
only to put it on.
Put it on, take it off, say שמע, Shema, I don't know.
גמרא Gemara doesn't say anything about taking it off. They used to
wear it the whole day, right? Well that's a question whether they
actually did. In theory you're supposed to, whether they actually did is
another question. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says אמר רב יהודה
קשר של תפילין צריך שיהיה למעלה כדי שישראל יהיה למעלה. Amar Rav
Yehuda kesher shel tefillin tzarich sheyehei lemala kedei sheyisrael yehei lemala. It
should be above which basically means you know not like at the
back, not below like below your hairline at the sort of closer
to the shoulder but actually what's called the nape of the neck?
Yeah so actually where we put it is where you can feel
the bottom of the bone before there's like a little indent here
in the back of your neck. Right the bottom of your skull
but it's high you know not at the very low part of
the neck. Why? כדי שישראל יהיה למעלה ולא למטה. kedei sheyisrael yehei
lemala velo lemata. That Israel should be above and not below. Now
again that's pretty bizarre. So is it פסול if I do it
otherwise? I mean that's a nice דרש, drash, you know what's he
saying like there should be nice symbolism or is he actually saying
no this is a real הלכה and now let me give you
a little דרש? drash? Again not clear. I wanted to say something
though about the ישראל למעלה ולא למטה Yisrael lemala velo lemata which
does tie into the קשר של תפילין kesher shel tefillin. because the
גמרא Gemara in ברכות Berakhot that talks about God wearing תפילין tefillin
says what's written in God's תפילין? tfillin, Does anybody remember though what
the גמרא Gemara says? מי כעמך ישראל גוי אחד בארץ.
Mi
ke'amcha Yisrael goy echad ba'aretz.
So the same way our תפילין tfillin speak about our holding God
up high and recognizing God above us in a way God's תפילין
tfillin, is expressive of his relationship with בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. So
the idea למעלה... lemala... ישראל יהיה למעלה ולא למטה Yisrael yehei lemala
velo lemata is not that we should be our you know we
should be thinking about God and God should be above, ישראל למעלה
ולא למטה Yisrael lemala velo lemata is I think directly in the
context of the מדרש midrash he just said before about the קשר
של תפילין. kesher shel tefillin If you want that's the most I
could say about what it means that God משה Moshe saw the
back of God. The רמב"ם, Rambam, famous רמב"ם Rambam says what does
it mean you know רמב"ם Rambam of course always very bothered with
the anthropomorphisms. What does God mean when he says to the רמב"ם...
Rambam... when he says... that's a good question. What does God mean
when he says to משה you'll see my... you'll see my back
and not my front? So God says it means you can't truly
understand what I God am but you can see how I act
in the world and you can sort of see my if you
will my ways my you know my echo of my presence and
that's my back. So in a way if the תפילין tefillin, are
מי כעמך ישראל גוי אחד בארץ Mi ke'amcha Yisrael goy echad ba'aretz
and it talks about God's relationship to בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, so
seeing the קשר של תפילין tefillin, is somehow seeing you know the
how God about how God acts within history and in terms of
God's relationship to Israel.
They're discussing God's tefillin right now.
You know they also... they also don't know that God wears תפילין.
tefillin, What does the whole thing mean anyway?
What are you tying to?
You know I think we have to open up God's תפילין tefillin.
and see if he פוסק paskens like רש"י Rashi or רבינו תם
which was what we read yesterday about the שו"ת מן השמים. Shut
Min Hashamayim. Alright so now the גמרא Gemara says like this
and then somebody else mentioned something about the
order of the פרשיות parshiot as כסדרן. kesidran. You know this idea
that you know that the reader... to the right of the reader
or the left of the reader... Right you can't read inside the
box. And then the rear wearing it...
oh you mean the קשר is the only thing you can see.
Yeah maybe. Oh the same way the שין shin is a part
that you can actually see so there's that power there right. Right.
I did want also mention, I know we're further more behind, yeah,
the שין shin in the גמרא Gemara? just says the שין. shin.
תוספות Tosafot there quotes the שימושא רבא Shimusha Rabba we won't read
it inside but on the previous דף daf again this ספר שימושא
רבא that speaks about having a one side having a three-armed שין
shin and the other having a four-armed שין. shin. And that's what
we do although again like now. not in the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*,
it's from the ספר *sefer* called the שימושא רבא *Shimusha Rabba*, but
again he was probably reflecting what practices were. And some say that
the point about the four, four-armed שין *Shin* is, is that it
all—no, well, maybe, to represent the four פרשיות *parshiyos*,
it also represents the space between those arms, you know, you can
fit upside down into a four-armed שין *Shin* a three-armed שין *Shin*.
If you imagine this creating, right, if you imagine the white space
here, an upside down white space of a four, of a three-leg
שין *Shin*, you know, fits into a four-leg שין *Shin*. And that
actually is what תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* says. And part of that has
to do with the idea again about like, you know, is it,
you know, makes you think about the sort of לוחות *Luchos* that
God gave, you know, the space as opposed to the, you know,
that the, there were, the letters were formed by cutting through and
the space, and how much is it sort of, you know, the
word, you know, what sort of we're seeing or what God is
seeing, I don't know,
it's a very mystical four-leg שין *Shin*. What? Who's to say that
with a modern Hebrew? Couldn't it have been cuneiform?
Could have been, but we're writing it in Assyrian Hebrew, so...
well, אש שחורה *esh shechora* על גבי
*al gabei* אש לבנה *esh levana* maybe? That's my point! Wow, oh,
the black! Oh, and this is the אש לבנה *esh levana*, so
there's what to do with that.
Why do we care that it's a three-armed שין *Shin*?
I don't know why we care. Somehow, has to do something with—I
really don't know why we care. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says... so moving on. Okay, וצריך שיסיימו כלפי פנים כדי שישראל
לפנים ולא לאחור *V'tzarich sheyisyimu k'lapei pnim k'dei sheyihyu Yisrael lifnim v'lo
l'achor*. It had to be facing front, that whatever, what facing front
means is a little unclear. We're back to the קשר *kesher* של
*shel* תפילין tefillin *tefillin*. And רש״י *Rashi* says what it means is
that probably just means the black is on the outside and the
white is on the inside, it has to be facing properly, that
ישראל *Yisrael* should be in front and not behind. אמר רב שמואל
בר רב יצחק אמר רב ואמרי לה אמר רב אחא בר יעקב
אמר רב הונא ואמרי לה אמר רב מנשיה אמר שמואל תפילין tefillin.
מאימתי מברך עליהם *Amar Rav Shmuel bar Rav Yitzchak amar Rav v'amrei
lah amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov amar Rav Huna v'amrei lah amar
Rav Menashya amar Shmuel tefillin me'eimasai mivarech aleihem*. Okay, moving on. Now
we've got the physical boxes of the תפילין tefillin *tefillin*, okay, and
now we have the question about the putting them on. When do
you make the ברכה beracha. *bracha*? משעת הנחתן mishas hanachasan, *Mish'as hanachasan*,
from the moment that you place them on. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says, איני *eini*, is that really true? והאמר רב יהודה אמר
שמואל כל המצוות כולן מברך עליהן עובר לעשייתן *V'ha'amar Rav Yehuda amar
Shmuel kol hamitzvos kulan mivarech aleihen over la'asiyasan*, before you do it.
משעת הנחתן mishas hanachasan, *Mish'as hanachasan* sounds like you already put it
on.
אביי ורבא דאמרי תרווייהו משעת הנחה hanacha.
ועד שעת קשירה keshira, *Abaye v'Rava d'amrei tarvaihu mish'as hanacha v'ad she'as
kshira*. No, we mean you place it on your hand, you make
the ברכה beracha *bracha*, you place it on your head, you make
the ברכה beracha? *bracha*, and then you tighten it. Then you do
the קשירה kshira *kshira*. So you do it right before you do
it, we don't mean after you place it on, we mean between
the time when it's ready to go on and then the ברכה
beracha. *bracha* and then the actual tightening. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says here עד שעת קשירה ad shas kshira, *ad she'as kshira*. There's
a very interesting תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* that says, takes the word קשירה
kshira *kshira* literally, and says that what this means is, I'll just
give you the first line, משעת הנחה ועד שעת קשירה kshira *Mish'as
hanacha v'ad she'as kshira*, מכאן היה מדקדק רבינו אליהו שצריך אדם לקשור
תפילין le-kashair tefillin בכל יום yom, *mikan hayah medakdek Rabbeinu Eliyahu shetzarich
adam likshor tefillin bechol yom*, that you do not just tighten your
תפילין tefillin. *tefillin*, that you come every morning, you've got to come
earlier to שול *shul*, and basically you take, you have your box,
you have your strap, and you start making the loops and making
the knots and doing the whole thing and actually tightening and making
it, and then he says probably maybe that's only on the של
יד shel yad *shel yad*, not the של ראש shel rosh *shel
rosh*. But you can imagine what that would be, you're actually doing
the קשר *kesher*, not just the tighten. Partly though why does תוספות
Tosafot *Tosfos* say this? He says because we've got a פסוק pasuk
*pasuk*, that's how he reads קשירה *kshira* in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
And then he says, no, קשירה *kshira* is לאו דווקא davka *lav
davka*, קשירה *kshira* means tightening, not knotting. But תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* says
I have a פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, right, what does the פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* say? He says, if you take a
look תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* says like this, he says at the top
of ל״ו *Lamed Vov* עמוד amud א׳ *Amud Aleph*, תוספות Tosafos *Tosfos*
says like this: ומסתברא
*u'mistavra*, one, two, three, three lines down in the narrow lines, middle
of the line, ומסתברא כדברי רבינו תם בתפילין של ראש shel rosh.
*u'mistavra k'divrei Rabbeinu Tam bitfillin shel rosh*—Rabbeinu Tam says you don't have
to make the קשר *kesher*, that's on the תפילין tefillin של ראש
shel rosh, *tefillin shel rosh*—וכדברי רבינו אליהו בתפילין של יד shel yad,
*u'k'divrei Rabbeinu Eliyahu bitfillin shel yad*, why? כדכתיב בשל יד yad וקשרתם
Ukshartem לאות l'ot על ידך *Kedichsiv b'shel yad u'kshartam l'os al yadecha*,
דמשמע דכל שעה שמהניח צריך לקשירה זה *demashma dechol sha'ah shemaniyach tzarich
likshira zeh*. You've got to make a knot. You gotta love it,
passing a straight פסוק *pasuk*. Okay, the פסוק *pasuk* says make a
knot, so therefore maybe by the של יד shel yad *shel yad*
you actually need to make a knot. Now, of course it's pretty
funny, it's pretty funny in the immediate context of having learned about
מזוזה *mezuzah*, where it says וכתבתם על מזוזות ביתך *u'chsavtam al mezuzos
beisecha*, and you actually don't take out your quill and start writing,
right. So his point is, you know, you made a קשירה *kshira*
and now by having it is doing the מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*, but
תוספות Tosafos *Tosfos* wants to say maybe we read this literally. And
maybe, David, your point, I was also thinking about the ideological point,
it's a lot easier to make this like loop thing of the
של יד shel yad *shel yad* than it is to make this
complicated knot of the של ראש shel rosh *shel rosh*, at least
the way we make the knot of the של ראש shel rosh...
*shel rosh*. So also, allowed for...
Don't you already have a loop that you're tightening? What? Your של
יד shel yad *shel yad* has a loop that you are...
Yeah, I know, but רבינו אליהו *Rabbeinu Eliyahu* says that doesn't count.
You have to actually put the strap into the תפילין tefillin *tefillin*,
make the loop, make the knot... Or he just means the י׳
*yud*, making the י׳ *yud* on there? Just make that every day?
I don't think so. I think he means putting the strap into
the תפילין tefillin. *tefillin* and connecting. Now, of course it's a little
bit funny because וקשרתם ukshartem *ukshartam*, does that mean you should make
a knot on your תפילין tefillin. *tefillin*? It means you should, you
should bind your תפילין tefillin *tefillin*, not your תפילין *tefillin*... to and
onto your arm. So, but maybe it is that you do the
whole knotting, you put the whole loop in, you do the whole
binding, not just the tightening. So, anyway, it's hard to understand like
why that פסוק is so compelling since it's really about connecting it
to your arm, which is what we do do. But what it
does point to, and we will see this in a minute when
we get to the different ברכות berachot you make, is the different
verbs that the תורה uses. A more active verb by the של
יד shel yad. and a more static verb by the של ראש.
shel rosh וקשרתם u-keshartam, as opposed to והיו. vehayu. So תוספות Tosafos
here is thinking it might make a difference whether you have to
actually make the knot or not. Let's keep on going as the
גמרא talks about the specific ברכות berachot that you make.
And the תוספות would be right, making it not every day?
ולפי רבינו אליהו U'leefi rivinu Eliyahu would. אמר רב חסדא, Amar Rav
Chisda, so רב חסדא Rav Chisda says, סח בין תפילה לתפילה חוזר
מברך. sach bein tefillah l'tefillah chozer mevarech. If somebody talks between the
תפילה tefillah l'תפילה, tefillah, we're normally not used to seeing these words
in the singular, it does not here mean a prayer, if you
talk between the של יד shel yad and the של ראש, shel
rosh. you have to go and make another ברכה. beracha, Now the
גמרא says, well, what does that mean? סח Sach in only if
you spoke, you did a הפסק, hefsek, לא סח lo sach not
if you didn't. והא שלח רב חייא בריה דרב הונא משמיה דרבי
יוחנן, V'ha shelach Rav Chiya brei d'Rav Huna mishmei d'Rabbi Yochanan,
we have a letter sent in the name of
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan from ארץ ישראל, על תפילה של יד אומר
al tefillah shel yad omer ברוך אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו להניח תפילין.
Baruch Asher Kideshanu B'mitzvotav V'tzivanu L'haniach Tefillin. על של
ראש, Al shel rosh, on the של ראש shel rosh what do
you say? ברוך אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו על מצות תפילין. Baruch Asher
Kideshanu B'mitzvotav V'tzivanu Al Mitzvat Tefillin. Okay, now, before we get to
how this is relevant to one ברכה beracha or two ברכות, berachot,
which it obviously is, the question is what's the different נוסח. nusach.
So רש''י Rashi says the different נוסח nusach is ל li is
imperfect, it means you're not done yet, so you're still in the
process of the להניח. l'haniach. על מצות Al mitzvat is when you
have the של ראש, shel rosh. it's all done, so now you
can talk that the מצוה mitzvah, was completed. But I would understand,
not, not me, others say, greater and much greater than I, point
out that the difference is exactly reflecting the פסוקים. pesukim. That the
וקשרתם u-keshartam לאות is an active verb, so you say להניח l'haniach
that it's to do an action to put on the תפילין. The
של ראש shel rosh is a static verb, והיו לטטפת, vehayu l'totafot,
על מצות, al mitzvat, on the status of תפילין, on the מצוה,
mitzvah the מצוה mitzvah, is completed but it's not about an action
of doing, it's about having the תפילין on me on on me.
So two ways of understanding the different נוסח הברכות nusach haberachot and
what we see is there are two ברכות. berachot. So why did
we say only if you spoke between the two do you make
a second ברכה? beracha. Here we say you anyway make a second
ברכה. beracha So let's see what the גמרא answers.
אביי ורבא דאמרי תרוייהו, Abaye v'Rava d'amri tarvaihu, they both say לא
סח מברך אחת סח מברך שתים. lo sach mevarech achas sach mevarech
shtayim. Okay, if you didn't talk you only make one ברכה, beracha
if you talk you make two. So the פשט pshat of this
גמרא is that if you don't talk you just make one ברכה
beracha? on both of them, and that was his statement of
if you talk you have to make another, if you don't talk
you just make one ברכה. beracha When we said there are two
different ברכות, berachot, that happened, that's what happens if you do talk.
If you do talk then you make two different ברכות, berachot, although
he didn't say that. That is what רש''י Rashi says, that is
מנהג ספרד. minhag Sefarad. מנהג ספרד Minhag Sefarad is that they do
not, they only make one ברכה beracha on תפילין unless for some
reason
you know there was some הפסק hefsek between the two of them.
מנהג אשכנז Minhag Ashkenaz what? להניח. L'haniach. They say להניח. l'haniach. Okay
and only if he knows הפסק hefsek now because basically it's one,
you conceptualize it as although it's true אין מעכבין זה את זה,
ein me'akvin zeh et zeh, which we haven't gotten to yet, and
you can do של יד shel yad, without של ראש shel rosh
or whatever, when they come together they form a larger complete process
and it's one complete מצוה, mitzvah. so one ברכה beracha goes on
both sides. תוספות raises interesting questions, we're back to do בדיקת חמץ,
bedikat chametz, I we don't have time I can't go into this,
תוספות about what happens when you're מפסיק mafsik other things which are
processes. Do you have to make another ברכה? beracha So there's one
thing like בדיקת חמץ bedikat chametz which is clearly one thing, one
process, not multiple little things. There are other things which are much
more clearly very distinct things that I'm doing all at the same
all sequentially, talks about שחיטה. shechitah. I have a thousand chickens that
I'm going to שחט. shecht. I say אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו על
השחיטה Asher Kideshanu B'mitzvotav V'tzivanu al hashechitah and I start shechting, I
don't make it before each one. What happens if I מפסיק? mafsik?
Very clearly they're different acts that are just happening in sequence. And
then you have our case which is somewhere in between. Because on
the one hand you don't, if you do יד yad without ראש
rosh or ראש rosh, without יד yad you're יוצא. They're not like
בדיקת חמץ, bedikat chametz, it's all one thing concept, but on the
other hand it's not like שחט shechting a lot of chickens, they
combine to form a larger מצוה. mitzvah, So what constitutes a הפסק
hefsek could be different in all those three scenarios, you know, because
you're trying to get your ברכה beracha to go on multiple things
or on one thing and so on. So that's one question about
what constitutes a הפסק hefsek about talking. I want to though talk
about the importance of the difference between the ספרדים Sefardim and the
אשכנזים Ashkenazim in question about the ברכה beracha that you make, because
if you make basically the ברכה beracha of, oh I didn't say,
did I say the other read of the גמרא? The other read
of the גמרא, which תוספות says is, if you're if you're לא
סח lo sach then, we're talking about the של ראש. shel rosh
You always make a ברכה bracha. on the של יד, shel yad.
אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו להניח תפילין. Asher Kideshanu B'mitzvotav V'tzivanu l'haniach tefillin.
Now when it talks about the ברכה bracha on the של ראש,
shel rosh and you always make the ברכה bracha. of על מצות
תפילין al mitzvat tefillin like רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan sent, that's true,
you always make those two ברכות. berachot. When does סח sach matter?
About whether the של ראש shel rosh, is going to get just
one ברכה bracha or two ברכות. berachot. So if I talk between
the של יד shel yad and the של ראש... shel rosh, then
on the של ראש shel rosh I'm going to say להניח lehaniach
and על מצוה. al mitzvah. And if I don't talk, then I'm
just going to do one on the של יד shel yad and
one on the של ראש. shel rosh That's how the אשכנזים Ashkenazim
פסקן. pasken. That we do one on the של יד shel yad
and one on the של ראש shel rosh. if you talk and
you מפסיק, mafsik, you make two on the של ראש. shel rosh?
By the way, there's a there are cases where this is הלכה
למעשה. halacha le-ma'aseh. I mean, besides if you talk. Or for example,
let's say somebody can't put on a של יד. shel yad Somebody
has a cast or let's say וזאת החדיתא ve-zos hachadisa or no,
doesn't have an arm, right? What do you do? So there are
they are separate מצות mitzvos and you would put on the של
ראש shel rosh. and you'd make both ברכות, brachos, okay? So that's
the way for the ספרדים Sefardim you'd make the one ברכה. bracha
So that's the difference. So both אשכנזים Ashkenazim and ספרדים Sefardim do
agree that if you're not שח, sach, the ברכה bracha on the
של יד shel yad. goes on the של ראש shel rosh and
we see it as like one larger מצוה, mitzvah one larger process.
If you do שח sach then you have to look at it
as a separate מצוה mitzvah. and therefore it gets its ברכה. bracha
The debate is as to whether you always also acknowledge the של
ראש shel rosh as something distinct. If you with the אשכנזים Ashkenazim
always acknowledge, you know, you have like both things going on. Each
thing retains its distinct identity and it's part of a process. That's
the way I would say, you know, part of a whole. That's
I would say the אשכנזי Ashkenazi way. להניח, lehaniach, על מצוה, al
mitzvah, each one separate. On the other hand, they are all, you
know, they are also parts so the להניח lehaniach has to go
on the של ראש shel rosh as well. Or the way the
ספרדים Sefardim say it is that no, if you, you know, if
you don't have a need to to single out the status of
the של ראש, shel rosh you don't, and it's one ברכה bracha
on all. The other interesting thing to note is both אשכנזים Ashkenazim
and ספרדים Sefardim both agree that the ברכה bracha, of להניח lehaniach
goes on the של ראש, shel rosh which is again interesting.
על מצוה al mitzvah you mean?
No, להניח. lehaniach. When you say להניח, lehaniach, that also relates, it
covers the של ראש shel rosh and the evidence is that when
you're מפסיק, mafsik, now you have to make a separate להניח lehaniach
on the של ראש shel rosh both for אשכנזים Ashkenazim and ספרדים.
Sefardim. Well, no, for the ספרדים Sefardim actually it becomes a על
מצוה. al mitzvah.
רבותינו, Rabbeinu, and if we talk according to the ספרדים Sefardim then
what happens? Then you have to make it על מצות al mitzvas
also on the של ראש. shel rosh, And להניח lehaniach again or
not?
No. Anyway, without talking, it's getting a little complicated and we need
to move on, but the point I just want to make is
thinking about how much again going back to the פסוק of וקשרתם,
how much is the idea of an action of binding a concept
that applies to the של ראש? shel rosh, Okay, and for the
אשכנזי Ashkenazi you actually, you know, if you don't have your של
יד, shel yad you're going to say two ברכות brachos on the
של ראש. shel rosh להניח lehaniach and על מצוה. al mitzvah. That
shows that even for the אשכנזי Ashkenazi just the של ראש shel
rosh, by itself, or should talk, the של ראש shel rosh by
itself, the concept of an action of putting on applies. For the
ספרדים Sefardim it's less clear because if you just have the של
ראש shel rosh. by itself, you do על מצות. al mitzvas. And
when you have both, you do להניח lehaniach but your primary focus
then is on the של יד. shel yad So you never have
a להניח lehaniach focused on the של ראש shel rosh for the
ספרדים. Sefardim. So I the point I want to get at out
of all of this is going back to that תוספות about the
about the language in the פסוק is how much is the של
ראש shel rosh basically a static and how much is there a
concept of an action of putting it on? We saw about תוספות
about the קשירה, but it's also a question about the נוסח הברכה
nusach ha-bracha and might break down to the ספרדי-אשכנזי position. Okay, but
again for the אשכנזים Ashkenazim you always will make a separate ברכה
bracha, as we know on the של ראש shel rosh and for
the ספרדים Sefardim only if you're מפסיק mafsik between the two of
them.
Well moving two ברכות brachos about the act of shel.
Well again, that's the point I
said,
these are separate מצות.
mitzvos. פסקן. pasken. פסקן. pasken.
What you're saying is though
these are two ברכות המצוה birchos ha-mitzvah is what he's saying. According
to the אשכנזים, Ashkenazim, there it's a ברכת הנהנין birchas ha-nehenin and
a ברכת המצוה. birchas ha-mitzvah. Here what you're saying is that it's
two ברכות המצוה, birchos ha-mitzvah, which you're right, is a funny idea
according to the אשכנזי Ashkenazi thing, according to the אשכנזי Ashkenazi approach.
But it may point out to two dimensions of their מצוה. mitzvah
There's a מצוה mitzvah to do the act of putting it on
and then there's a מצוה mitzvah to have it on you. That's
the וקשרתם והיו. ve-hayu. But still, you're right. Since when do even
if a מצוה mitzvah, is complex and it has two dimensions, since
when would we make two ברכות המצוה? birchos ha-mitzvah?
Is it maybe similar to what you're saying before how there's two
elements of קדושה, kedusha, there's...
Oh, I don't see it that way. I see this related to
whether it's to put it on or to have it on.
Wouldn't you expect that the ברכה bracha? would be לקשור le-kashair תפילין
as opposed to להניח? lehaniach?
So that's a very good question and, you know, if anything, it's
a good challenge to the רבינו אליהו ותוספות. Rabbeinu Eliyahu ve-Tosafot. Maybe
we specifically did not say לקשור le-kashair? because we don't actually make
the קשר. We put it on ourselves, so it's a really strong
question. I mean, I hadn't connected it that way, but you're right.
According to him, we make this the נוסח הברכה nusach ha-bracha here,
why not say לקשור? le-kashair. Right.
But we could make it on the on the יד yad
and call what we're doing לקשור. Right. It's a good point. Yeah.
Is ברכת התורה birchas ha-Torah ברכה ארוכה bracha aruka or or two
different ברכות? brachos?
Well, ah, that's a good point. You know, ברכת התורה birchas ha-Torah
is a good example and ברכת התורה birchas ha-Torah might be a
hybrid of a ברכת המצוה birchas ha-mitzvah אשר קדשנו asher kiddishanu but
a ברכת השבח birchas ha-shevach אשר בחר בנו מכל העמים. asher bachar
banu mi-kol ha-ammim. But there are מחלוקות machlokos about whether we dominate
we look at ברכת התורה birchas ha-Torah as dominantly a ברכת המצוה
birchas ha-mitzvah or dominantly a ברכת השבח. birchas ha-shevach. So that's a
good example where you have multiple dimensions being reflected in multiple ברכות.
brachos. James's point is still good that I don't know of any
other case that you have two אשר קדשנוs asher kiddishanu on one
מעשה מצוה. ma'aseh mitzvah. And even if we can argue that it's
a מעשה מצוה ma'aseh mitzvah that has two dimensions to it, which
is so maybe that's part of the problem with why the like
the ספרדים Sephardim don't like the אשכנזי Ashkenazi approach, you know, that
they say in principle, the של ראש shel rosh requires two ברכות
המצוה birchos hamitzvah is an idea they're not ready to embrace.
They only have the head, they
only say
והניח, v'hanich, I mean על מצוה, al mitzvah, על מצוה. al mitzvah.
They will never say להניח l'haniach on the head, they'll say להניח
l'haniach on the יד yad which also goes on the head and
they'll say על מצוה al mitzvah on separate ones on the head.
We talked, right. Okay, so now the גמרא says like this, all
right. So תנו, tano, we taught in a ברייתא, Braisa, סח בין
תפילה לתפילה, sach bein tfillah l'tfillah, if somebody talks between the two
תפילין, עבירה היא בידו, aveira hee b'yado, it's a sin, וחוזר עליה
מערכי נחמה. v'chozer aleha me'orchei nochama.
And if you're going out to war, right, so you know it
says מי האיש הירא ורך הלבב, Mi ha'ish hayarei v'rach haleivav, so
the גמרא says that means רך הלבב מן העבירה שבידו, rach haleivav
min ha'aveira she'b'yado, so even if you just talk between the של
יד shel yad and the של ראש, shel rosh that's a reason
to go back, which is supposed to impress us with how weighty
the sin is, or is it the opposite? It's a very small
sin, but the point is you can go back for war even
for the most smallest of sins. Not exactly clear, it seems like
it's more of the former. Yeah, so רש"י Rashi says it means
you talked between the two and you didn't make the right ברכה
bracha, afterwards.
Because if you do that ברכה, bracha.
you, but I would say this is an important question, which is
not clear, is the problem of talking just the problem of requiring
a ברכה, bracha a new ברכה? bracha תוספות gets into a whole
discussion of how big of a problem is the idea of ברכה
שאינה צריכה. bracha she'eina tzricha. You know, so what? So he talked
to make a ברכה, bracha, so תוספות says למה לו, lama lo,
that's also an עבירה, aveira, you required a ברכה שאינה צריכה, bracha
she'eina tzricha, you required another ברכה. bracha So רש"י Rashi and תוספות
work within it within the context of you didn't make the right
ברכה bracha or you did a ברכה שאינה צריכה bracha she'eina tzricha
and so on. But the other question is, going back to this
idea that if we see these as not two independent מצות mitzvos
but as some joint, each one is independent but they also are
a joint larger מצוה, mitzvah and the evidence being that the ברכה
bracha on the של יד shel yad normally does apply to the
של ראש, so maybe even if you do make the right ברכה,
bracha there's an עבירה, aveira, there's an עבירה aveira of separating the
מצוה mitzvah. of תפילין as a separate של יד shel yad. and
של ראש מצוה. mitzvah The goal is to make it a unified
process. So even if you solve the ברכה bracha problem, you still
have separated the process, and the גמרא's not clear that the entire
problem here is the ברכה bracha problem. Okay, let's keep on going
a little more. תנו, tano, we taught in a ברייתא, Braisa, כשהוא
מניח מניח של יד ואחר כך מניח של ראש. k'shehu meniach meniach
shel yad v'achar kach meniach shel rosh.
When you put it on, first you put on the של יד
shel yad and then the של ראש, וכשהוא חולץ חולץ של ראש
ואחר כך חולץ של יד. uk'shehu choletz choletz shel rosh v'achar kach
choletz shel yad. And when you take it off, you first take
off the של ראש and then the של יד. shel yad.
Why is that?
בשלמא כשהוא מניח מניח של יד ואחר כך מניח של ראש, bishlama
k'shehu meniach meniach shel yad v'achar kach meniach shel rosh, I understand
when you put it on, first put on the יד and then
the ראש, דכתיב וקשרתם לאות על ידך והדר והיו לטטפת בין עיניך
d'chtiv uk'shartam l'os al yadecha v'hadar v'hayu l'totafos bein einecha in the
order. Now again, notice the idea that we are treating this as
one מצוה mitzvah, process. It's not like you have two separate מצות
mitzvos to do. Here's a process of putting two things on, which
is the order that you put them on. So again, this is
sort of part of the interesting thing about תפילין, you can do
one without the other, but when you do both, it's part of
one big complete larger מצוה, mitzvah, which as I said, is I
think part of the problem about סח, sach, not just the ברכה
bracha problem. So I get the order when you're putting it on.
אלא כשהוא חולץ חולץ של ראש ואחר כך חולץ של יד מנלן?
ela k'shehu choletz choletz shel rosh v'achar kach choletz shel yad minalan?
Who says that when you reverse the order, I care which order
you reverse it? So אמר רבה, amar Rabba, so רבה Rabba said,
רבה בר רב הונא אסברה לי, Rabba bar Rav Huna asberah lee,
רבה בר רב הונא Rabba bar Rav Huna explained it to me,
אמר קרא והיו לטטפת בין עיניך, amar kra v'hayu l'totafos bein einecha,
they shall be as לטטפת, totafos, והיו v'hayu is plural. Okay, although
לטטפת totafos is also plural. Here we're choosing to use the word
והיו v'hayu to refer both to the של יד and the של
ראש. וקשרתם לאות והיו uk'shartam l'os v'hayu means the two of them
shall be. So כל זמן שבין עיניך יהיו שתים. kol zman she'bein
einecha yehu shtayim. Whenever you have the של ראש and it's בין
עיניך, bein einecha, both of them should be on you. So the
של ראש should be building on the של יד and therefore you
should not take off the של יד if you would rip the
foundation out from underneath. Okay, you have to build so the של
ראש is only when there's also a של יד and it builds
on the של יד. Again showing somehow the dependency, not really הלכתית,
halachically, you can have one without the other.
Right, I was gonna say.
But ideally the dependency of the two and how they function together.
I would also say what's fascinating about this is again the difference
of the action versus the status. והיו, v'hayu, be. So it's meaning
the action is first do A then do B. Then the question
is the state. What is the state? So there's a state of
being wearing them both and the idea of the של ראש requires
also the wearing of the של יד and that's more about not
the action but about the state. So now when I'm picking it
off I should not live in a state where I have the
של ראש on without the של יד.
Pretty close to הלכות ברכות halachos brachos what some would say. Yeah.
If there's a separate מצוה, but it's also
על המצות al hamitzvos and when we had פסח Pesach did they
make both ברכות? brachos? That would have been an interesting question. Right
now nowadays we have only the על אכילת מצה. al achilas matzah.
If you had בזמן הפסח, bizman haPesach, would you say, so there
is a נוסח הברכה, nusach habracha, אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו לאכול מצות,
Asher kidishanu b'mitzvosav v'tzivanu l'echol matzos, you know עם מרורים, im m'rorim,
לאכול קרבן פסח עם מצות ומרורים l'chol Korban Pesach im matzos u'mrorim
or whatever, you know על מצות ומרורים יאכלהו, al matzos u'mrorim yochluhu,
when they said that would they also then say אשר קדשנו במצותיו
וצונו על אכילת מצה? Asher kidishanu b'mitzvosav v'tzivanu al achilas matzah? Why
not? You know but that is a good example, I mean whether
they would do that or not I don't know, but that would
be an example where you had two very different roles of that.
True. Let me just read through the... bottom of the דף. daf.
We're already late and I just want to finish the bottom of
the דף. daf. Let's take a look. תנו רבנן: Tannu rabbanan: מאימתי
מברכין עליהן? me-eimasai mevorchin aleihen? So תפילין, מאימתי מברכין עליהן? me-eimasai mevorchin
aleihen? When you make the ברכה bracha on תפילין, yeah, משעת הנחתן,
from the time you put them on. So in a way we
just had that, but now we're going to say that it really
means also from the time that they're allowed to be on, which
means what?
כיצד? keitzad? היה משכים לצאת לדרך, haya mashkim latzes laderech, you woke
up early and you had to put on your
תפילין, you didn't want to carry them in your bag, you wanted
to wear them, וירא שמא יאבדו, veyarei shema yovdu, you thought if
you put them in your knapsack they'd get lost or something. So
מניחן, menichan, put them on now even though it's not yet daybreak.
וכשיגיע זמן ממשמש בהן ומברך עליהן. uch-she-yagia zman memashmesh bahen umevarech aleihen.
And when the time comes, then you touch them, you feel them,
and you make a ברכה bracha, because the touching and the feeling,
that's sort of like a new placing on. Now, this is again
a beautiful example of those
two דברים devarim of רב יעקב Rav Yaakov of קשירה versus הנחה.
And notice how this spilled off of the phrase משעת הנחתן, although
before we objected to the phrase and then we said, no, no,
it means עד שעת קשירה, but here we're saying that the קשירה
went before, the קשירה is the real action, but if the act
of putting them on was done before the right time, before daybreak,
you can make the ברכה as if you would, a whole other
way to reframe the גמרא is you can make the ברכה כל
זמן שמניחן, kol zman she-manichan, as long as you're still wearing them,
you can make the ברכה because the importance is not just the
initial act, but the state of wearing. So therefore, okay, but it's
over for the next second you're about to wear it. And therefore,
so that is actually what we say, you know, if you're wearing
ציצית tzitzis from before, you feel your ציצית and you make the
ברכה, you feel your תפילין. So again, what's very nice about this
is it's pointing again to the idea of the state of wearing
תפילין and not just the act of putting on תפילין. And let's
just finish this out.
ועד מתי מניחן? ve-ad masai menichan? How long can you keep them
on? עד שתשקע החמה, ad she-tishka hachama, until sunset. There's two reasons
why you don't wear תפילין at night. One is לילה לאו זמן
תפילין, layla lav zman tefillin, which is basically learning from the פסוקים
pesukim that, you know, it says we'll see in a minute, somehow
that it's a דין din of יום, yom, like a lot of
other מצוות mitzvos that apply during the day. And the other is
a concern that you'll fall asleep and you'll pass gas and that's
not keeping the קדושה kedusha of the תפילין. Okay, so once it's
sunset.
Do you think there's a later time for that too, meaning would
רבינו תם agree that like, you know, the second... Oh, the second
שקיעה?
shkia?
Yeah, yeah. And I also think, why am I remembering that some
people דווקא have a מנהג of putting on רבינו תם תפילין Rabbeinu
Tam tefillin after שקיעה shkia and before צאת? tzeis?
Maybe because in פיצויים pitzuyim there's this opinion.
Maybe, but I also think it should be בל תוסיף, bal tosif,
I don't know. Anyway, רבי יעקב אומר עד שתכלה רגל מן השוק.
Rabbi Yaakov omer ad she-tichleh regel min hashuk. No, it's not just
after sunset. Like חנוכה. Chanukah. Right, after sunset and until everybody gets
home because that's when people start getting ready for bed and so
on, because it's a clear concern not of a הלכה definition of
לילה layla and יום, if it's not about a פסוק it's about
falling asleep. So as long as there's still business on the street
we don't care. וחכמים אומרים עד זמן שינה. vachachamim omrim ad zman
sheina. No, no, even if the people are all home, until it's
normally bedtime for you or yeah, for most people, whatever, it's not
an issue. So the last two opinions clearly are a concern you'll
fall asleep and pass gas. The first one sounds like a more
formalist approach that it's a concern of the definition of night versus
day. ומודים חכמים לרבי יעקב, umodim chachamim l'Rabbi Yaakov, and חכמים chachamim
agree to רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov שאם חלצן לצאת לבית הכסא או
ליכנס לבית המרחץ. she-im chaltzan latzes l'veis hakiseh o likanes l'veis hamerchatz.
So here you get taking your תפילין off for going to the
bathroom. If you took them off ושקעה חמה vashakha chama and then
it was sunset, so then they would agree שוב אינו חוזר ומניחן,
shuv eino chozer umenichan, you do not put them back on. So
they'll let you keep them on until it's time where people fall
asleep, but they won't לכתחילה lechatchila say you're allowed to put them
on. So the normal way of explaining this is again, it's a
concern of passing gas, it's a רבנן rabanan concern. We don't force
people to take off תפילין until it's really a problematic time, but
לכתחילה lechatchila we would say don't put it on once it is
nightfall. אמר רב נחמן, Rav Nachman and רב נחמן says, הלכה כרבי
יעקב, halacha k'Rabbi Yaakov, we rule like רבי יעקב, Rabbi Yaakov, which
is עד שתכלה רגל מן השוק. ad she-tichleh regel min hashuk. Which
basically means it's getting to be after sunset but it's also getting
to be that the business is ending in the street and conceptually
what that means is לילה layla is זמן תפילין, zman tefillin, but
it's a concern of falling asleep and passing gas. Are early in
Riverdale?
עד שתכלה רגל מן השוק? ad she-tichleh regel min hashuk? Yeah, right,
when the stores close?
Yeah, okay right, depends if you live in Manhattan. רב חסדא ורבה
בר רב הונא, Rav Chisda ve-Rabba bar Rav Huna, so רב חסדא
Rav Chisda and רבה בר רב הונא Rabba bar Rav Huna מצלו
בהו באורתא. matzlu behu be-orta. They prayed while wearing תפילין. Presumably they
prayed מעריב Maariv while wearing
תפילין. איכא דאמרי... Ika d'amri... what does אורתא orta mean? At night.
Okay, איכא דאמרי. Ika d'amri.
איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, some said, אין הלכה כרבי יעקב, ein halacha
k'Rabbi Yaakov, that we do not rule like רבי יעקב. Rabbi Yaakov.
Did I skip a line?
Yeah... No, I didn't. Okay. איכא דאמרי אין הלכה כרבי
יעקב,
ein halacha
k'Rabbi
Yaakov, that we don't rule like רבי יעקב. Rabbi Yaakov. So if
we don't rule like רבי יעקב, Rabbi Yaakov, what do you do
with... so then this praying with them at night, before a minute
ago it was a support that you're allowed to keep them on
after sunset. But now we don't rule like רבי יעקב, Rabbi Yaakov,
and if sunset you take them off, what were they doing wearing
them? והא רב חסדא ורבה בר רב הונא מצלו בהו באורתא, ve-ha
Rav Chisda ve-Rabba bar Rav Huna matzlu behu be-orta, they did pray
with them at night. הנהו פליגי, hanhu peligi, okay, that was arguing.
So fine, there's a debate. They thought that you can wear them
and others think that you can't. So we are going to continue
with this tomorrow. We're still an עמוד behind, thankfully not more, about
the question about whether you can keep תפילין on at night or
whether you
should take them off, which is the question about whether לילה layla
is לאו זמן תפילין lav zman tefillin which would require you to
take it off, or whether it's a concern of falling asleep which
would not require you until it gets much later. See you tomorrow.